Shuyu Zhang

Lecturer of Biology at Our Lady of the Lake University

zhangtreefish@yahoo.com

Summary

I researched bacterial conjugation and stress adaptation and authored nine peer-reviewed articles. I currently develop and teach college biological courses, and have expertise in science education, from course conceptualization, development to instruction. From my work of course design, I am veering into frontend web development. In my spare time I act as a linguist (language pair: Mandarin/English), write about healthful foods, and volunteer in the community.

Experience

Lecturer of Biology at Our Lady of the Lake University

January 2015 - Present (5 months)

Teach a Lab section of Introduction to Life Sciences

Instructor at Hallmark College

June 2011 - October 2014 (3 years 5 months)

Developed and instructed courses including Microbiology, Anatomy and Physiology, Nutrition and Wellness, and Business Statistics, Math Foundation, and Character Education Course Dependability.

Postdoctoral Fellow/Research Instructor at UTHSCSA

October 1998 - March 2006 (7 years 6 months)

Conducted scientific research on topics of cancer biochemistry at the Institute of Molecular Medicine, and on the mechanism of bacterial stress response at the Department of Microbiology and Immunology.

Certifications

Drugs and the Brain

Coursera February 2013

Cardiac Arrest, Hypothermia, and Resuscitation Science

Coursera July 2013

Introductory Human Physiology

Coursera May 2013

Vaccines

Coursera November 2013

Intro to HTML and CSS

Udacity September 2014

JavaScript Basics

Udacity September 2014

Linguist in Life Science

TransPerfect 2006

Languages

English

Mandarin

(Native or bilingual proficiency)

(Native or bilingual proficiency)

Skills & Expertise

Molecular Biology

Microbiology

Biochemistry

Immunology

Teaching

Flow Cytometry

Laboratory

Protein Purification

Biotechnology

Nutrition and Wellness

Cancer

Genetics

Cell

Cell Biology

PCR

DNA

Genomics

Protein Expression

Education

Linguist, Mandarin Chinese-English

Anatomy and Physiology

Blackboard Learn

HTML

CSS

Git

jQuery

JavaScript

Education

Udacity

Nanodegree, Front-End Web Developer, 2015 - 2015

Hallmark College of Technology/Hallmark College of Aeronautics

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Global Management, 2013 - 2014

Grade: 4.0

The University of Texas at Austin

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Microbiology, 1992 - 1998

Tsinghua University

Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, 1986 - 1991

Activities and Societies: Chorus.

1 recommendation available upon request

Interests

Learning, health, world peace.

Projects

a Frogger game

February 2015 to March 2015

Members:Shuyu Zhang

a Frogger game with an immunology twist using Object-Oriented javaScript and HTML5 Canvas:

Publications

Contributions of ATP, GTP, and redox state to nutritional stress activation of the Bacillus subtilis sigmaB transcription factor.

Journal of Bacteriology 2005

Authors: Shuyu Zhang, William. G. Haldenwang

Changes in ATP level inside the soil bacterium Bacillus subtilis are critical to its adaptation to nutritional stress.

Localized Denaturation of oriT DNA within Relaxosomes of the Broad-host-range Plasmid R1162

Molecular Microbiology 1997

Authors: Shuyu Zhang, Richard Meyer

Unveiling of the change in DNA structure as it prepares to spread to another bacterium.

Volunteer Experience

San Antonio Healthy Food Examiner at Examiner.com

May 2011 - Present (4 years 1 month)

Write articles about healthy foods in San Antonio.

Usher at Tobin Center for the Performing Arts

October 2014 - Present (8 months)

Direct the flow of patrons at the Tobin venues.

Shuyu Zhang

Lecturer of Biology at Our Lady of the Lake University

zhangtreefish@yahoo.com



1 person has recommended Shuyu

"Shuyu has great commend of both Chinese and English."

— Yan Isabel Zhu, Student, Tsinghua University, studied with Shuyu at Tsinghua University

Contact Shuyu on LinkedIn